<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A call to weeping: or A warning touching approaching miseries In a sermon preached on the 20th of March, 1699. At the funeral of Mrs. Elizabeth Westen, late wife of Mr. John Westen, who departed this life on the 17th of the said month, in the 38th year of her age. By Benjamin Keach.</title>
            <author>Keach, Benjamin, 1640-1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B25417</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829212</idno>
  <idno type="VID">207117</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240861332</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing K52</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829212</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99829212e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B25417)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 207117)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1991:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A call to weeping: or A warning touching approaching miseries In a sermon preached on the 20th of March, 1699. At the funeral of Mrs. Elizabeth Westen, late wife of Mr. John Westen, who departed this life on the 17th of the said month, in the 38th year of her age. By Benjamin Keach.</title>
                  <author>Keach, Benjamin, 1640-1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>56, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for, and sold by John Marshal at the Bible in Grace-Church-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 5 reads: A call to vveeping, or a vvarning touching approaching miseries. Demonstrated in a sermon preached at the funeral of Mrs. Elizabeth Westen late wife of Mr. John Westen.</note>
                  <note>With two final advertisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Congregational Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:207117:1"/>
            <p>A <hi>Call to Weeping:</hi> OR A WARNING TOUCHING <hi>Approaching Miseries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a Sermon Preached on the 20th of <hi>March,</hi> 1699. At the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Westen,</hi> late Wife of Mr. <hi>John Westen,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted this Life on the 17th of the said Month, in the 38th Year of Her Age.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Benjamin Keach.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>Gen. 46. 35, 39.</bibl>
            <q>And Rachel Dyed and was Buried.—And Jacob set up a Pillar upon her Grave; that is called the Pillar of Rachels Grave unto this Day.</q>
            <bibl>Psalm 112. 6.</bibl>
            <q>The Righteous shall be in Everlasting Remembrance.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed for, and Sold by <hi>John Marshal</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Grace-Church-street,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:207117:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207117:2"/>
            <head>To his Honoured (though sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful) Friend, Mr. <hi>John VVe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Cannot but be deeply sensible, and much affected, and sympathize with you in your great Loss; but the Consideration of the Happy End and Triumphant Death of your dear Yoke-fellow may greatly moderate your Sorrow. O with what <hi>Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> of Joy was she filled! it may well be said of her, she went away Singing; if any thing may convince this <hi>Atheistical Age</hi> of the Truth or Verity of <hi>revealed Religion,</hi> one would think the beholding how some <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in Christ go out of the World,</hi> might do it. <hi>Sir,</hi> forbear Mourning, <hi>She is not Dead, but sleepeth,</hi> and that in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus too;</hi> Her <hi>better Part</hi> could not <hi>Die,</hi> because she truly <hi>believed</hi> in Jesus Christ; She has left you, but is gone to him, which to Her <hi>is far better.</hi> I hope you and others will never forget that wholesom and Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Advice she gave, to Love God, and to
<pb facs="tcp:207117:3"/> live to him who willingly became <hi>a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for our Sins.</hi> I was much affected, when I heard what a Text she had left to be opened at her <hi>Funeral;</hi> But since it was your Purpose and Resolution to <hi>Publish</hi> the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, it would have been well, had I had a little more Time for my Study, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration (for the Lords Day intervening, I had indeed but a few Hours) so that I hope you and others, who either heard the Sermon or now shall read it, will over-look my weaknesses; some few things are here added, which were then omitted for want of Time; and that a Blessing from the <hi>God of Truth</hi> may <hi>accompany</hi> it, and make it profitable to all that Love the Lord Jesus in <hi>Sincerity</hi> (who shall vouchsafe the Pains to peruse it) shall be the Prayers, Sir,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Of your most affectionate Brother in Christ, and Unworthy Overseer, Benj. Keach.</signed>
               <dateline>Horsly-Down, <date>March <hi>23d.</hi> 1699.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:207117:3"/>
            <head>A Call to VVeeping, or a VVarning touching ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Miseries.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Demonstrated in a Sermon Preached at the Funeral of Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Westen</hi> Late Wife of Mr. <hi>John West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>LUKE XXIII. xxviii.</bibl>
               <q>Weep not for me, but weep for your selves, and for your Children.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AMongst the many Motives to a Holy and Pious Life, the Sense of Death and of Eternity is one. Many live as if this World would never end; and as if the World
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:207117:4"/> to come would never begin: And tho' Death makes so great a Change, yet how little is it thought of by the Generality of People.</p>
            <p>Indeed, one of the greatest Motives to Holiness, is the Mercy of God, and a lively Sense of his Infinite Love in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ. <hi>I beeseech you by the mercy of God, that ye present your bodies a living sacrifice, holy and acceptable unto God, which is your reasonable service,</hi> Rom. 12. 1.</p>
            <p>God's Wrath being over in Jesus Christ, our Sins Pardoned, and He fully Reconciled, how should this move us to live to Him, who died for us, and rose again. <hi>Shall we sin that grace may abound? God forbid,</hi> Rom. 6. 2. We being made free from Sin (as the Apostle shews) <hi>should have our Fruit unto Holiness,</hi> and so <hi>our End</hi> will be <hi>Everlasting Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One End, Purpose, and Design of God in that Redemption we have by Jesus Christ, is, <hi>that we should be to the Praise of the Glory of his Grace, wherein he hath made us accepted in the Beloved,</hi> Eph. 1. 6. My Brethren, as we were chosen in Christ to be Holy, so to this End I say we were Redeemed; <hi>Who gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self for us, that he might redeem us from all Iniquity, and purchase to himself a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:207117:4"/> People zealous of good Works,</hi> Tit. 2. 14. Moreover God is Holy, and we are called with an Holy Calling, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we should be Holy. Likewise ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great Motive hereunto, is those high Priviledges and precious Promises made unto us in Jesus Christ; as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle shews, 2 <hi>Cor. 6. 17, 18. Wherefore come out from among them, and be ye sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate saith the Lord, and touch not the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean thing, and I will receive you.</hi> He saith more, <hi>I will be their God, and they shall be my People.</hi> Nay, he saith, <hi>I will be a Father unto you, and ye shall be my my Sons and Daughters, saith the Lord Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</hi> And in <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. 1. Saith <hi>Paul, Having these Promises (dearly Beloved) let us cleanse our selves from all filthiness of the Flesh and Spirit, perfecting Holiness in the Fear of God.</hi> Many think, the grand Motive to Holiness is our own Happiness; they strive to lead a Pious Life that they may be saved, and it may be feared 'tis that they trust to, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie upon; whereas the Argument to true Piety with true Christians, is, because they are saved, 'tis to Glorifie God. Our inherent Holiness is not our Title to Eternal Life, though it is that which tends to make us meet for it; yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:207117:5"/> there are many other Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to stir us up to a most serious and pious Life, and amongst them those ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the Consideration of Death are none of the least; I have read that <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon</hi> commanded one of his <hi>Pages</hi> to wake him every Morning by crying at his Chamber Door, <hi>Sir remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you are a Man:</hi> He disdained not to be put in mind of his uncertain Breath by his sorry Page; we ought to consider the Certainty of Death, and yet the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of the Time, every one must say with <hi>Isaac, I know not the Day of my Death.</hi> Likewise to consider, what the Effects of Death will be, to some it will be an Hour of Sorrow, though to others an Hour of Joy? Was it not a sad <hi>Bill</hi> that was put up to me <hi>Yesterday,</hi> of one that said, <hi>He was so Sick he could not Live, and so sinful he durst not Dye:</hi> To one the Thoughts of Death is cause of Weeping, but to another a cause of Weeping, but to another a cause of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, which brings me to the Words of my Text.</p>
            <q>Weep not for me, but weep for your selves, and for your Children.</q>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:207117:5"/>
            <p>These Words were spoken by our Blessed Saviour, when they were lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to <hi>Golgotha</hi> to be Crucified, and such was their Cruelty, that they laid on him the pondrous Cross, till (as it is thought) he fainting in the way, they compelled one <hi>Simon</hi> a <hi>Cyrenian</hi> to bear part of it, and so <hi>Matthew, Mark,</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> may be reconciled with <hi>John,</hi> who says our Saviour bore the Cross.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>good Women</hi> who loved him dearly, sorely wept to see what their Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Lord had already suffered, and was fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther now likely to undergo by the Rage of his bloody Enemies; and this was the occasion of these Words, <hi>Daughters of Jerusalem, Weep not for me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Daughters of Jerusalem,</hi> both of the Litteral and Mystical <hi>Jerusalem:</hi> In my Text are two Parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Dehortation, <hi>Weep not for me.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. An Exhortation, <hi>but Weep for your selves, and for your Children.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>A little by way of Explination.</p>
            <p>In the Negative Part, or Dehortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, something may seem difficult, for <hi>ought we not to Weep and Mourn in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Thoughts of what our Lord Jesus en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:207117:6"/> and suffered for us?</hi> What not one Tear for a bleeding Jesus!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Answer,</hi> It is certainly our Duty to Weep bitterly; as I shall shew you by and by. Therefore the Words of our Lord are to be taken with Restricti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> They ought not to Weep inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinately, all inordinate Passion for the Sufferings of Christ (which possibly might rise in some of those Women from natural Love and Affection) may be here forbid; was it not possible for some of those Women to have a natural as well as a Divine Love to the Lord Christ; he was nearly related to some of them in the Flesh, and shall such a Friend, such a Relation Dye unbewailed? No! No! He did not forbid them thus to Weep, but he would not have them exceed therein; for [not] doth not imply, <hi>not at all</hi> in many Places of the Scripture, but is to be taken with Restri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> They were not to Weep without Hope, touching the Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Blessed Lord; <hi>Weep not for me</hi> (as if he should say) for though I must Dye, yet I shall (as I have told you) on the Third Day rise from the Dead;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:207117:6"/> and you shall see me again; and I shall Dye no more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They were forbid to Weep without Faith, and the certain Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the grand End and Design of his Death, which it appears for some time they were (or at leastwise some of them) ignorant of; for when our Lord told his Disciples that he should Die, <hi>Peter</hi> replied, <hi>far be it from thee Lord;</hi> and this also further appears by what he said to some of them, after he rose from the Dead, <hi>Luke 24. 25. O Fools, and slow of Heart to believe all that the Prophets have spoken, ought not Christ to have suffered these Things, and to enter into his Glory?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> They were not to Weep, as if he could not have saved himself from Death, or on a Supposition, that they took away his Life by force, or against his Will; no, Weep not (as if he should say) for no Man taketh my Life from me; for I freely laid it down of my self, I voluntarily surrender up my self to Die: Indeed, if his Life was taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way against his Will, or if he had not Power to save himself from Death, it might render him miserable; nay, and worse Consequences would then follow also; therefore, let me add here a few
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:207117:7"/> Arguments to prove he Died voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There was no more Necessity lay in God to Redeem <hi>Mankind,</hi> then to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem the <hi>fallen Angels?</hi> nor is he any more happy or glorious in himself hereby, though his Glory greatly herein appears to his Creatures which he hath made.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And as it was a meer soveraign Act of Grace in God the Father, so likewise it was a meer soveraign and voluntary Act of Free Grace and Love in God the Son, which moved him to become a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; for was there any Necessity of Nature that lay upon the Son of God to enter into that Blessed Covenant with the Father in Eternity, upon our Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count? Was he forced so to do against his own Will and Inclination? No, no, he was at Liberty, whether he would e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spouse our Interest or not, it was a pure voluntary Act rising from himself; God being one, he Acts as one and the same God. Evident it is, that the
<note place="bottom">This I purposed to have delivered in this Sermon, but had not Time, but think good to add it, since it is Published.</note>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:207117:7"/> Work of Redemption comported with the Wisdom and soveraign Love and Goodness of the whole Trinity; I say, there was no Necessity or Force put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Christ to assume our Nature, and to Dye for us: True, perhaps there was a Necessity for him thus to do, if we were ever redeemed, and also after he had voluntarily entered into that Covenant with God the Father, or had struck Hands with the Father; but his striking Hands, I say, was a free and voluntary Act of his own soveraign Grace, and Love to Gods Elect; (and wonderful love it was indeed in him to become our <hi>Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and Saviour,) which will further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, if we consider these few Things following.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He was not ignorant before he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came our Surety, that the whole Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our vast Debts would fall upon himself: Alas! others would never <hi>strike Hands</hi> in <hi>Suretiship,</hi> if they knew, or <hi>foresaw</hi> that they must <hi>pay</hi> the Debt for the <hi>Debtor;</hi> but the Son of God well knew this, and yet freely undertook for us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He was not ignorant what he was to be made, even <hi>a little lower then the Angels,</hi> yea poor and contemptible for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:207117:8"/> our Sakes. <hi>You know the Grace of the Lord Jesus Christ, that though he was Rich, yet for our sakes become Poor, that we through his Poverty might be made Rich,</hi> 2 Cor. 8. 9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He was not ignorant of that Death, that Cursed and Ignominious Death he was to Die, and yet freely undertook the Work of our Redemption, he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saw (being God) what a bloody Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny he was to fall into, and how his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (he standing in our Law-place) would hide his Face from him in the midst of his other Sorrows.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He was not ignorant of their great unworthiness (for whom he came to dye and suffer such inconceiveable Miseries) who were naturally his Enemies, and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Rebels against him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Nor was he ignorant, how long some of those Sinners for whom he Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed would resist him, and refuse the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of his Love and Favour; nay, would let him stand <hi>knocking and waiting at their Doors,</hi> after he had done all in Point of Sacrifice, and Payment of their Debts.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Neither was he ignorant of our Unkindness, and abuse of his Love and infinite Favour; after we came to receive and accept of the offers of his Grace, and cleave to him; and yet for all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:207117:8"/> this, he freely struck Hands with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in that blessed Covenant.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But doth not our Lord say, that it behoved him thus to Dye, or that he ought to Dye?</hi> Was he not then constrained so to do, <hi>thus it is written, and that it behoved Christ to suffer,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 46.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Answer,</hi> This refers to Christ as cloathed with our Nature, and as one that had engaged himself to suffer in our stead; considered as Mediator, he become God's Servant, and it was then indeed necessary. See <hi>Charnock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God (as one well observes) cannot be forced to do any thing against his Will, and if Christ had been thus compelled, there had indeed been Cause for the <hi>good Women</hi> to Weep. Besides, also no Man is, or can be forced against his Will to become a Surety, the Obligation requires that the Act be free and voluntary, and that the Person be at his own free dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal in that Matter, as I might further shew.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But did not our Saviour shew some kind of Ʋnwillingness in his bloody agony? If it be possible, let this Cup pass from me.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:207117:9"/> —Father, save me from this Hour,</hi> John 12. 27.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answer,</hi> This struggling might rise from the Humane Nature; though the Humane Nature of Christ was Innocent, yet it was weak; as one observeth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This may shew, that our blessed Lord was really Man as well as God, yea God-Man in one Person.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As God he knew what he was to suffer, but as Man <hi>he made Supplication with strong Cryings, and Tears, and was heard in what he feared,</hi> Heb. 5. 15. It was not, as our Divines observe, from any unwillingness that was in him to Dye, but from the sense of that Wrath which began to lie upon his Soul, which we must have born for ever, had he not born it for us, or in our stead: This therefore shews that what he felt and suffer'd was intolerable to Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, unless supported by the Infinite Deity.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He saw the comfortable Influences of God suspended, and felt the Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God due to us for our Sins, break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out upon his Human Soul and Body; and also the Law letting fly all its Curses and fiery Darts against him. God is the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:207117:9"/> object of Fear in his Vindictive Justice, his Wrath is terrible, and from hence he might cry out and speak these words, that we may know the evil of sin, and the greatness of that Wrath which he bore that was due to us; and also to deter all wicked men from their sins, and to make them sensible of that pain and anguish they are like for ever to undergo, that so they may fly to Jesus; and that Believers may prize and love their Saviour with the greater affection.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It may be to shew to us, that there was no other way to save our Souls from Hell, <hi>If it be possible let this Cup pass from me:</hi> If it may comport with thy Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Justice and Holiness, let me be spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; but he knowing this only was the way God had found out, cried, <hi>not my will, but thy will be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. It might be to shew, how we in most dismal afflictions should learn of him to submit unto the Will of God.</p>
            <p n="7">7. May be it was not consistent (as Worthy <hi>Charnock</hi> notes) with that Reverence which Christ always shewed to God, had he not been sensible; and also had not shew'd how sensible he was of the sharpness of that Punishment which he must bear, as he was a constituted-Sinner in our stead.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:207117:10"/>
            <p>Further more, saith this Author (with others before him) <q>Though the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of our Saviour was but one, yet he having Two Natures, had Two Wills, a <hi>Divine,</hi> and a <hi>Humane Will;</hi> otherwise he were not God and Man: If he had not a Humane Soul, he was not Man; and if he had not a Humane Will, he had not a Humane Soul. As truly as he took our Nature, so he took the Laws of it, whereby it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not effect Pain, but shun whatsoever it apprehends is hurtful to it.—As Wrath was an Evil against Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, Christ desired to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline it; but as it was an Atonement for Sin, and to appease God's Wrath, and save his People through the worth of his Sacrifice, so he desired to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He willingly Suffered, it appears,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By his entering so freely from all Eternity into Covenant with the Father for us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By his chearful coming into the World to do his Father's Will, it was his Meat and Drink. <hi>Lo I come to do thy Will, O God,</hi> Heb. x. 5.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By declaring that his delight was with the Sons of Men, <hi>Prov.</hi> viij. 31. from everlasting.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:207117:10"/>4. By his own Expressions concerning his laying down his Life, <hi>John</hi> x. 17, 18. <hi>Therefore doth my Father love me, because I lay down my Life, that I may take it up again. No man taketh it from me, but I lay it down of my self: I have power to lay it down, and have power to take it up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. By his saying, to this end he came into the World.</p>
            <p n="6">6. By saying, How am I straitned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til this work is accomplish'd, <hi>Luke</hi> xij. 50.</p>
            <p n="7">7. How did he rebuke <hi>Peter,</hi> when he said, <hi>Lord, far be it from thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. By saying, <hi>The Cup which my Father gives me to drink, shall I not drink it,</hi> John xviij. 11.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Also how freely did he surrender himself, <hi>Whom do ye seek? Jesus of</hi> Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth; <hi>I am he.</hi> He was God, therefore could not be constrain'd; it had been Injustice to punish an innocent Person forced to become a Surety.</p>
            <p>The Merits of his Sufferings also de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended upon the Father's Acceptance, and the Son's Voluntary Obedience, as all our Reverend Writers do accord. So that from the whole I infer, They were not to weep through the Ignorance
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:207117:11"/> of this Matter, as thinking his Life was forced from him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Neither should they weep as if he was by Death made misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Some in Death are undone for ever, <hi>viz.</hi> they die and are Damned to an endless Eternity: May be <hi>David</hi>'s fear touching the State of <hi>Absolom,</hi> made him weep so bitterly for his Death, who died in Rebellion against his Father; but my Brethren, although great Wrath, and the horrid Guilt of our Sins lay on Christ, yet he was not utterly forsaken and deserted of his Father, because he fully satisfied his Divine Justice, and could plead in the midst of his Anguish his Interest in God, <hi>My God, my God, why hast thou forsaken me?</hi> He knew full well all his Sorrows would be soon over, therefore could not be lamented as one miserable and for ever cast off by the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed God. Death hereby was conquered, <hi>by Death he destroyed Death, and he that had the power of Death, which is the Devil, and delivered them who through the fear of Death were all their lives time subject to Bondage,</hi> Heb. ii. 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> It was his Father's Will (as you have heard) that he should die, nay the result of that blessed Counsel held in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:207117:11"/> Eternity, <hi>him being deliver'd up by the determinate Counsel and Foreknowledge of God, ye have taken, and by wicked Hands have Crucified and Slain;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were not to weep in oppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to, or, as being ignorant of the Will and Purpose of God, touching his Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> They were not to weep, as being ignorant of that great Glory which his Death would bring unto God, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect unto all the Glorious Attributes, and <hi>how Mercy, Truth and Justice would hereby meet together, and Righteousness and Peace kiss each other,</hi> Psal. lxxxv. 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> Nor should they weep, as being Ignorant of the necessity of his Death, if ever we are Redeemed; nor of that infinite Good that would hereby redound to all God's Elect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly,</hi> They should not weep, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Death would put an end to all his Sorrows and Miseries, whose whole Life was a Life of Trouble, and therefore he was called <hi>A Man of Sorrow, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with Grief.</hi> What shall he now be near to his happy Deliverance out of this miserable World, so as never to know or feel Pain and Misery more, and shall his dearest Friends weep?</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:207117:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Tenthly</hi> and Lastly, They were not to weep, because by Death he should be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted, and enter into his Glory. <hi>For we see Jesus, who was made a little lower than the Angels, for the suffering of Death crowned with Glory and Honour.</hi> He me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited a Crown of Glory for himself, and for all his Elect; <hi>Therefore will I divide him a Portion with the great, and he shall divide the Spoil with the Strong, because he poured forth his Soul unto Death, and he was numbred with Transgressors;</hi> Psalm liij. 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In the Affirmative, <hi>We may, nay ought to weep, and be affected and afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for what Christ suffered for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>1st.</hi> Because our sins were one cause of his Suffering; our Sins slew him, and may be said to be the Spear that pierced his tender Heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Because of the Bitterness of his Sorrows and Sufferings for us. Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is so far lawful to weep upon this account, that it is a sin not to do it: And now that this is our Duty, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears,</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the Type, <hi>the Passover was to be eaten with bitter Herbs;</hi> and what did that figure forth, but that we who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:207117:12"/> Jesus Christ should feed by Faith upon him in the bitter sense of our Sins, that put him to so much Pain and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Because it is the effect of saving Grace: Such that receive the Grace of God in Truth are moved to mourn for him. <hi>I will pour upon the House of David, and upon the Inhabitants of Jerusalem the Spirit of Grace,</hi> &amp;c.—What then? what Effects will this have on their Hearts? <hi>They shall look upon me whom they have pierced, and they shall Mourn for him, as one mourneth for his only Son, and shall be in bitterness for him, as one that is in bitterness for his first-born,</hi> Zech. 12. 10.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Because of the great Dignity of his Person, he was God Co-equal with the Father, his Eternal Son; <hi>The bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the Fathers Glory, and the express I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of his Person,</hi> Heb. 1. 1, 2, 3. What not one Tear to see such a Person hang on the Tree, and lie bleeding on the Cross? He that was the Darling of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the Object of the Fathers most choice Affections, and the Delight of his Soul: Shall he be afflicted by Heaven, Earth, and Hell, and we be not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d? Shall <hi>Judas</hi> one of his own Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:207117:13"/> betray him, <hi>Peter</hi> deny him, and the Father forsake him, and we not Mourn?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Consider, for whom he died, were they his Friends, or such that loved him, were they deserving Persons, were they such that were Lovely, and might draw his Affections by the Excellency of their Beauty; or such that could ever requite him, for such Expressions of his Love and Favour; No, no, not Friends but Enemies, not well deserving but ill deserving, nay Hell deserving Creatures; not beautiful and nobly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended, but vile, loathsome, and filthy Creatures, base Born, and the offspring of an ignoble and cursed Stock, and such that were never able to make him the least Recompence.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Is not the Holy Supper ordained, partly to move our Affections, and melt our Souls into Tears; hath he appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an Ordinance to represent his bloody Passion, and set before our Eyes, how his Body was broken, and his Blood poured forth; and would he not have us Weep upon the sight and thoughts thereof? No surely, and would he have this often repeated, and yet not have our Souls affected? certainly this cannot
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:207117:13"/> be his meaning: So much as to this.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Whereas our Lord said, <hi>Weep not for me,</hi> it may denote Three Things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. His fittedness or preparedness to Die.</item>
               <item>2. His willingness to Dye.</item>
               <item>3. His happiness in Death.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And thus it was, I doubt not, in a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, with our dear Friend Departed.</p>
            <p>She was prepared to Die, She was willing to Die, and was Happy in her Death, and therefore could say <hi>Weep not for me, but Weep for your selves, and for your Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From my Text thus opened, I shall observe two Points of Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Doct. I. <hi>There is no real Cause to Weep for such that are fitted and prepared to Die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doct. II. <hi>That there may be Cause to Weep for our selves, and for our Children, who servive.</hi> A little briefly to each of these Propositions. I shall in speaking to the first of them.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Prove it.</item>
               <item>2. Apply it.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:207117:14"/>1. Now that there is no Cause to Mourn or Weep for them that are fitted and prepared to Dye; (I mean upon their Account) may appear, and be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonstrated from the Considerations of those great Benefits such do receive at Death. My Brethren, most of that which a Believer hopes for he receives not until then, 'tis not in this Life, no, if <hi>in this Life only, we had Hope in Christ, we were of all Men most miserable,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. <hi>The Wicked is driven away in his Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness, but the Righteous hath Hope in his Death,</hi> Prov. 14. 32. The best of a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers Comfort begins when his Life ends; <hi>The Day of their Death is better then the Day of ones Birth,</hi> Eccl. 7. 1. But wo to the Wicked, Death is that terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Gate that opens unto them a fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, endless Eternity, and strips them of all their Rich Treasure and Honour. <hi>Wo</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>to you that are Rich</hi> (Rich but Ungodly) <hi>you have received your Consolation,</hi> Luke 6. 28. I have read of a <hi>Queen</hi> of this Realm, who said she <hi>preferr'd Her Coffin before Her Cradle,</hi> but every true Believer may prefer a Coffin before an Earthly Crown and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:207117:14"/>
            <p>A Believer at Death receives great Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and Immunities, History tells us of one, who after he had done most noble Exploits in a religious Way, <hi>begged of God that which would be most beneficial to him,</hi> who going to Bed slept his Last; which caused his Friends to say, Death was most profitable; But to descend to Particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> A Saint at Death obtains his Freedom, <hi>Apprentices</hi> and <hi>Bondmen</hi> long till their Time is out; our Time of Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and Servitude is not out till Death comes, then we are out of our Time in Eternity, and made Free for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> A Believer then is freed of the Body of Sin and Death, it may be called a Body, because of its weightiness; and a Body of Death, because of its Loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>someness, it is the Reliques of the worst of filthiness. <hi>O wretched Man that I am</hi> (saith <hi>Paul) who shall deliver me from this Body of Sin and Death,</hi> Rom. 7. 24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is a base <hi>Make-bate,</hi> that sets a Man against himself, others set one Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour against another, and that is a horrid thing; but this <hi>Make-bate</hi> sets a Man at Variance against himself, it puts all out of Order, and into Confusion in a Mans own Soul; so that his Peace is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally interrupted.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:207117:15"/>2. 'Tis like a Cursed <hi>Inmate,</hi> that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually disturbs us, but we can't warn him out, he is never dispossessed until Death comes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Or like <hi>Evil-seed,</hi> or a <hi>cursed Weed</hi> so rooted in our Garden, that we cannot pluck it up though it spoils the good Seed, and hinders the growth of all those precious Flowers planted therein.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Or it is like a <hi>filthy Ʋlcer</hi> that marrs our Beauty.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Or like a cursed Law which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroys our Liberty, and holds us in Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, or carries us into Captivity, being furiously executed by the Prince of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and that remaining Strength which he hath still in our Hearts.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Or it is like an <hi>evil Disease</hi> that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feebles, and debilitates all the Members, and Powers of the <hi>new Man;</hi> so that a Believer may say with <hi>David</hi> (hereby) <hi>I am become weak this Day, though anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed King,</hi> 2 Sam. 3. 39. These Sons of <hi>Zerviah</hi> are too often too hard for us; <hi>The good I would, I do not, but the Evil I would not that do I.</hi> Now Brethren we are not, cannot be freed from this Body of Sin until Death comes, and then we are for ever delivered from it, we put off our <hi>Body of Flesh,</hi> and Body of <hi>Sin,</hi> both together.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:207117:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Because at Death a Believer is freed from all his Fears. True, he is deliver'd from <hi>slavish-fear</hi> whilest he lives; Christ hath freed all that believe on him from the <hi>Servile-Tormenting</hi> Fear of Death, which Blessing they possess ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Degree, or Measure, and Exercise of Faith; but notwithstanding this, yet they are not delivered from all sorts of disquieting Fear until they Die.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Their own Sins makes them fear, least God should with-draw, or hide his Face from them.</p>
            <p n="2">II. They Fear the Consequences or Effects of the Sins of Professors, and of the horrid Sins of a wicked World: <hi>I am afraid of thy Judgments,</hi> saith <hi>David,</hi> and again saith he, <hi>at what Time I am afraid I will trust in thee.</hi> The dismal Dispensation of Gods Providences makes the best of Men to fear; nay, and this fear may soon, to purpose, distress the Living, <hi>Mens Hearts shall fail for Fear, and for looking after those things which shall come to pass,</hi> Luke 21. 26.</p>
            <p>O saith a Child of God, What will become of the Gospel? What will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the Churches? What will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of our Liberties? Of our Estates, of our Children, if God should leave us?
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:207117:16"/> How shall I stand at the overflowing of <hi>Jordan? How shall I escape all those Things, that shall come to pass and stand before the Son of Man?</hi> Do you not see a Cloud a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rising as big as a Mans Hand, which makes you afraid.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Because a Believer at Death is freed from all his Troubles and Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances to which whilst in this World he is subjected, Life and Sorrow (while we are here) are Married together, and Death only breaks those Bonds, <hi>Man is born to Trouble, as the Sparks fly upwards,</hi> Job 5. 7.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. At Death a Believer is freed from the Tyranny, and Oppression of the Ungodly; <hi>There the Wicked cease from troubling, and the weary are at rest,</hi> Job 3. 17. <hi>There the Prisoners rest together, they hear not the Voice of the Oppressor,</hi> verse 18. What can we look for or expect in this World but Tribulation, that Lion that now seems to be Chained, may soon be loosed again; we can't say, yet trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble shall not rise up the second Time, for until Satan is bound, the Godly must look for little Quiet.</p>
            <p n="5">V. A Believer at Death is freed from all his <hi>Care;</hi> the Mind of a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is full of perplexing Thoughts while
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:207117:16"/> he remains here, there is a Care though it is not sinful, yet it is afflictive; many a Believer is made to <hi>Eat the Bread of Carefulness,</hi> as well as to <hi>Drink the Water of Affliction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. At Death a Believer is freed from all <hi>Clouds,</hi> that oftentimes while here <hi>interpose</hi> betwixt his Soul and Jesus Christ; he loses too often the sight of the <hi>Sun of Righteousness,</hi> though it is so pleasant for his Eyes to behold him; <hi>the Children of the Day, and of the Light,</hi> may walk in Darkness, and have but little, nay no Light of Comfort at all, <hi>Isa.</hi> 50. 10.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. He is then freed also from all his Labour, all things here are full of Labour, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1. 8. Man is to eat his Bread with the Sweat of his Brows; there is the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of the Hands, and the Labour of the Heart, the Mind of Man is full of labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Cogitations to attain that which he pursues, <hi>Paul laboured more abundantly then them all,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 10. The Work of a Christian is laborious, but <hi>their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is not in vain in the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 58. Ministers are called <hi>Labourers, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we labour and suffer Reproach, know them that labour among you,</hi> 1 Thes. 5. 12. All that fear God find their hands full of labour, this is our working-time,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:207117:17"/> but at Death we go to Bed, <hi>Blessed are the Dead which Die in the Lord, from henceforth Yea, saith the Spirit, that they may rest from their Labour; and their Works do follow them,</hi> Rev. 14. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> We ought not inordinately to Weep for such that are fitted and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to Die; because Death is gain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, they gain, saith one, a Writ of Ease from all Trouble; I, but that is not all. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. They gain a perfect State, Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not to be attained to in this Life, but the Souls of Believers are made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect at Death, not before, nor after Death, but in Dying; our Breath, and the Pollution of our Souls depart toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we read of the <hi>Spirits of Just Men made Perfect,</hi> Heb. 12. 23. They are made perfect in Holiness, here we are delivered from the Guilt, Power, and Punishment of Sin; but at Death from the being of Sin, though we are sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in every Part while we live, yet 'tis but in Part, but at Death perfectly: Death therefore does more for Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, then all Ordinances do, or can do for them; they do not only obtain perfect Peace, or enter into Peace, but obtain also glorious Purity; not one vain
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:207117:17"/> Thought more shall their Souls be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lested with, nor any Temptation of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. <hi>He that is Dead, ceaseth from Sin;</hi> Death is the Passage into the <hi>True Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> that flows with Milk and Honey, with Innocence, and Happiness for ever; there is nothing which can disturb the Peace, or corrupt the Purity of the Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed that Die in the Lord: All the Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Soul are raised to the highest Degrees of Natural and Divine Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on now they are only renewed, but at Death elevated to the highest pitch; the <hi>Ʋnderstanding</hi> clear, the <hi>Memory</hi> firm, the <hi>Will,</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> ardent and vigorous.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They gain more clear and glorious sights of God in Jesus Christ, they are near the Throne and are in his glorious Presence; <hi>where there is fulness of Joy,</hi> and inconceiva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble <hi>Pleasures for evermore,</hi> How refreshing is the sight of Christ by by Faith, <hi>If now tho we see him not, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, we Rejoyce with Joy unspeakable, and full of Glory.</hi> What will the Fruition and clear Vision be? those Blessed Spirits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove behold the glorified Body of Jesus Christ, <hi>While we are at eme in the Body we are absent from the Lord,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 6.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They gain more <hi>Peace</hi> undisturbed Peace; we have Peace with War here,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:207117:18"/> but their <hi>war-fare</hi> is accomplished; we have Peace in Christ but they have Peace with Christ. A Woman whose Husband is a Thousand Leagues from her, yet hearing of him, and receiving Kind Tokens of his Love hath much Peace and Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but what is that to her enjoying his Presence and Company?</p>
            <p n="4">4. They at Death gain a <hi>better Place,</hi> they go from the <hi>Valley of Tears,</hi> to the <hi>Mount of Joy;</hi> from a place of Dragons, nay of Devils to a place where no Devil is, nor Diabolical Emissaries. It was a strange Saying of a <hi>pretty Child,</hi> about Six Years of Age, to his Mother not long since, and not far off of this place, <hi>Mother, I would not live here, but go to a place where there is no Devil.</hi> Indeed this World is full of Devils who <hi>go about like roaring Lions seeking whom they may devour.</hi> But there is no Devil above!</p>
            <p>They leave a poor Cottage to dwell in a Noble Palace. <hi>For we know that if our Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly House of this Tabernacle were dissolved, we have a building of God, an House not with Hands, Eternal in the Heavens,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 1.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They gain better Company; True, they had the Society of the Saints here; Ay, but they are such Saints that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:207117:18"/> often greived them, <hi>frail, and imperfect Saints</hi> too unconstant in their Love and wavering in their Affections, divided Saints, some of them too subject to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and revile each other, Saints that have their Spots, and many Blemishes; But they go to glorified Saints, who are all of one Heart, and not only one in Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, but in Judgment also; which agree and harmoniously sing Eternal <hi>Hosanna's</hi> to God and the Lamb.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They gain perfect Victory, Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Honour, white Robes and Coelestial Crowns are given unto them, <hi>Rev. 6. 9. I saw under the Altar the Souls of them that were slain for the Word of God—and white Robes where given to every one of them,</hi> &amp;c.<hi>—they cast their Crowns</hi> (at Jesus feet) <hi>Rev. 4. 10. or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. They hunger no more, and thirst no more, all Tears are wip'd from their Faces, they Sin no more, suffer no more, and die no more, their gain and blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness exceeds all our Thoughts, and expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite Desires; what short of the Eloquence and Experience of an Angel can set forth what they gain and possess above? besides that which Crowns all, is that the Life above is Eternal; as they have
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:207117:19"/> full Communion with Christ and enjoy the Fountain of Life, and swim in Rivers of Pleasures, so what can interrupt or put an end to their Happiness which is Everlasting or Eternal. Thus from the whole we may say, <hi>Weep not for them;</hi> there is no cause, these things being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered, but a little by way of improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>The <hi>Application.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. We infer, that there is a vast diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the State of Saints on Earth and the Saints in Heaven; the best of Men and Women here have <hi>bitter</hi> as well as <hi>sweet Sorrow</hi> as well as <hi>Joy,</hi> and <hi>Sin</hi> as well as <hi>Grace,</hi> they have their <hi>Buts,</hi> their <hi>Imperfections,</hi> we have not put off our <hi>Armor;</hi> but tho it be thus, yet must not the vertues of Saints be mentioned? do they deserve no Praise? because in some things they may not be Praise-worthy, the Scripture Records the Sins and Miscarriages of gracious Persons as <hi>Noah, Lot, Jacob, Moses, David, Peter,</hi> and many others also, but doth it not Record their vertues, or what was praise-worthy in them? a Saint carries all to Heaven with him, that was
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:207117:19"/> his Riches he carries his Gold thither, and leaves all his Dross behind him.</p>
               <p>Our Dear Friend departed, I am sure excelled many (though all have their Buts, their Weaknesses, their Infirmities) Yet <hi>Her Works Praise Her in the Gate.</hi> What Zeal for God did She shew, and what Love to his People? And how did She long to see Her Relations, and all those She dearly Loved to be in Christ. O the Prayers She put up for them, and the Pains She took with them, and the good Counsel She gave them, and O what a blessed End did She make? The <hi>End Crowns all,</hi> with what Joy was She filled? She even broke forth into Raptures of Joy; she would have none to Pray for Her Life; I am certain, our honoured Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath lost a dear and helpful Yoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow, and her Near Relations and Kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, a good Friend; and this Congrgation a good Member, yet mind the Text She Left, <hi>Weep not for me,</hi> &amp;c. No, no, there is no Cause in respect of Her, <hi>Death is gain</hi> to Her, <hi>She had hope in Her Death</hi> and let Her <hi>be had in Everlasting Remembrance,</hi> but it is loss to them She has left behind.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I <hi>Infer,</hi> that none are so Happy as Believers, neither are they so Happy
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:207117:20"/> whilest they Live, as they are when they Die.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Moreover, I <hi>Infer,</hi> there is a vast difference between the Death of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and the Wicked; the one are great Gainers, the other are great Lossers.</p>
               <p>1. The Wicked at Death are great losers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>They lose the World,</hi> which they valued above Jesus Christ, they lose their God, and what had they more? the World is their God, they lose their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, their Gold and Silver, which was their Hope, and Die not worth one Groate, they carry none of their Riches out of the World with them, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 7. They lose their Pleasures, and all their Honour, and are brought to Shame and Everlasting Contempt. <hi>Saladine</hi> a <hi>Turkish-Emperour,</hi> commanded after his glorious Victories, that a <hi>white Sheet</hi> should be carried before him to his Grave, upon the Point of a Spear, with this Proclamation, <hi>these are the Spoils that</hi> Saladine <hi>carrieth away with him of all his Triumphs, and Victories, of all the Riches and Realms that he had, now nothing is left but this Sheet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>They lose their hope;</hi> Wicked Men are full of Hope, of a better Life, but at
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:207117:20"/> Death all their Hope perishes, their Hope of long Life, their Hope of Heaven is then cut off, <hi>Job. 3. 14. Whose Hope shall be cut off, and whose Trust shall be as the Spiders Web.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>They lose their Souls,</hi> and nothing can repair that loss, <hi>What doth it Profit a Man, if he should gain the whole World and lose his own Soul,</hi> Mat. 16. 26. No Loss like this loss, many bewail the Body forsaken of the Soul; but O how should he be bewalled, that is for ever forsaken by the Blessed God: O there is ground to Weep indeed for the Ungodly, who at Death lose their Souls.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>They at Death lose Heaven;</hi> I mean, they then see that they have lost God, lost Christ, and have lost Heaven, and that too for the love to a cursed World, and through love to their base and filthy Lusts, they depart from him as being Cursed and undone Creatures for ever more; and are cast into Hell, in that hour their Breath departeth out of their Bodys, their Souls are in Torment; as it is said of the Rich Man's Soul. The <hi>Rich Man died,</hi> and what's next, <hi>in Hell he lifted up his Eyes being in Torment,</hi> Luk. 16. 23.</p>
               <p>4. <hi>We Infer,</hi> That there is no Reason
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:207117:21"/> for any true Christian to be unwilling to Die; are any unwilling to accept of the highest Perferment; is a young Prince troubled that his Coronation-Day is come, or an Heir that he is arrived to full Age, to inherit his Estate; doth a Virgin grieve that Her Wedding-Day is come, when she is to be Married to a great Noble, whose Goodness, Honour and Beauty is admir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able? or is a Man who is wearied with hard Labor, troubled to think he is going to rest? At Death a Believer's chiefest Preferment is come, his Coronation-day is come, his Marriage-day is come, and his weary Body then goes to Bed, and his Soul to Eternal Rest; <hi>Brethren,</hi> the Righteousness of Christ is our Title to Heaven, <hi>viz.</hi> his active, perfect, Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Law of God, but Death gives us the immediate Possession thereof.</p>
               <p n="5">5. We may therefore from hence also Infer, What great Folly they are guilty of that seek not this only Title to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, by laying hold of Jesus Christ by the Faith of the Operation of God, or through the Spirit do not seek a vital mystical Union with the Lord Jesus. Many think that their Faith, their Repentance, their Obedience, or their inherent Righteousness is their Title to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:207117:21"/> Heaven. O take heed, be not deceived by the Errors of these times if you have no other Title to Heaven, but what is wrought in you, or done by you; you will certainly at Death drop into Hell. Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may evidence the goodness of your State, but you cannot plead your Faith, nor your Holiness and sincere Obedience as that which gives you a Right and Title to Eternal Life. Tis only Christs Obedience, and yet without Faith no man is actually possessed of this Title, <hi>Christ in you the hope of Glory</hi> Col. 1. 27. <hi>He that believeth not shall be Damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> Mark. 16. 16.</p>
               <p>5. Here is Comfort to Dear Pious Relations, who mourn for the Deceased, your Wife is <hi>Taken away from the evil to come,</hi> and which Evil may soon come; your Friend is gone to Christ and when Christ comes she and all that sleep in Jesus will God bring with him: <hi>When Christ who is our Life shall appear, we shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with him in Glory,</hi> Col. 3. 4. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Weep not for Her, <hi>Weep not for me, but weep for your selves, and for your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This brings me to the <hi>second</hi> Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:207117:22"/>
               <p>Doct. II. <hi>That there may be cause to weep for our selves and for our Children that survive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. This also I shall endeavour to prove and demonstrate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Apply it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First.</hi> There may be cause to weep in respect of internal evils that we groan under.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly.</hi> In respect of external evils which we feel, and have cause to fear.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Weep for your selves (as if our Lord should say) for you are Left to combat stil with your Spiritual enemies, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Flesh,</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Devil:</hi> you have not yet put off your Armor, you are still and shall be afflicted <hi>with the Body of Sin and Death, we groan being burdened,</hi> 2 Cor. 2. 5, 4. We have peace but not without trouble, we have Light but not without Darkness, Joy but not without Sorrow, Honour but not without reproach, and dishonour; we have Faith but not without Doubts, especially it is thus with some of us; we have grace but not without Sins: we meet with sore Trials and Temptations from Satan
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:207117:22"/> and sometimes may be under the hidings ef Gods face and the withdrawing, of Jesus Christ, and be tossed as with a tempest and not comforted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> We may have cause to weep for our selves and for our Children, <hi>in respect of Eternal evils which we feel, and may fear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>From those Losses,</hi> and sad disappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which we do, and may meet with all; We perhaps, have <hi>sown much and bring in little, We eat and yet may be have not enough, Hag. 1. 6. Cloathed but not Warm, earn Wages, but put into a Bag with holes;</hi> God has strangely blasted Men in their Trades Callings and Expectations. O saith one, if the Times hold thus what shall I do for Bread for my Family? and says another, what shall I do to get Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to pay my Debts? distress of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Sirs, are come and a coming, and this may be cause for such to Weep that do survive.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>We may have Cause to Weep, from those Pains, Diseases, and sad Distempers, which afflict our Bodies;</hi> Many may and do Groan upon this Account.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>And also upon the Consideration of their Children,</hi> Who go on in the Broad-Way, taking wicked Courses, and seem
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:207117:23"/> to be wholly under the ruling Power of the God of this World, O saith the poor Father and the poor and sorrowful Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, this and that Child I think will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non break my heart, they are <hi>Stubborn,</hi> and <hi>Rebellious, Hardned,</hi> I fear in <hi>Sin,</hi> and regard not my Crys, nor my prayers and good Counsel; I know not what will become of their Bodies, but O what will become of their precious Souls, O their Souls! their Souls!</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The Inormities and great Evils of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors</hi> is cause enough to make us Weep and all that Love Jesus Christ, We may wish with <hi>Jeremiah, Oh that my Head were Water and mine Eyes a Fountain of Tears, that I might Weep Day and Night,</hi> Why what is the matter, <hi>they are an As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly of Treacherous-Men, They bend their Tongues like their Bow for Lies, but are not valliant for the Truth upon the earth, they proceed from Evil to Evil</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Take heed every one of his Neighbour and Trust not in a Brother</hi>—Jer. 9. 1. 2. 3. 4. If ever any Day lookt like the Day the Prophet saw, I think it is this, we may say with Paul, <hi>Many walk of whom I have told you of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and now tell you even Weeping, they are enemies of the Cross of Christ,</hi> Phil. 3. 18. How is Religion exposed, and Gods
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:207117:23"/> Name dishonoured, few have a heart to do for God, and some that God Stirs up with some degree of Zeal, are but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>samed, and vilified for so doing, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if things prosper not according to expectation.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Have we not cause to Weep for the horrid and Crying Evils and Abominations of this wieked Generation;</hi> Certainly, no times exceeded these upon this account, <hi>I beheld Trangressions and was grieved, saith David,</hi> Psal. 119. 158. Again, he saith, <hi>Rivers of Water run down mine Eyes because Men keep not thy Law,</hi> Psal. 119. 136.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And more directly to the purport and design of our Blessed Lord in my Text, We ought to mourn for our selves and for our Children in regard of those sore and bitter Calamities that are Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ching. Our Lord, no doubt, on this occasion gave these Women a hint of those lamentable and dismal distresses that were coming upon <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and on the whole Nation of the Jews, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Church of God; mind the words following, <hi>for behold</hi> (saith he) <hi>The Days are coming in which they shall say, Blessed are the Barren, and the Wombs that never bare,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:207117:24"/> and the paps which never gave suck, then shall they begin to say to the Mountains, fall on us, and to the Hills cover us,</hi> Luke 23. 29 30. <hi>For if they have done all these things to the Green Tree what will they do to the dry,</hi> ver. 31. Blessed are they (as if our Lord had said) that have no Children: no Sons to be exposed to War, Blood and Slaughter; no Daughter to be Ravished, and then fearfully mangled, and cut, and torn into pieces, which fell out upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them and their Children: Well and what of this (perhaps some may say) what is this to us? why Brethren, see now we are in Peace, Blessed be God, under a good King whom God in Mercy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, We have the Gospel, we have Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and Liberty, and set under our own Vines, and Fig-Trees, and none at the present make us afraid, but alas, alas! what evils are near we know not; may be God set this Text of Scripture upon the Heart of our dear Friend deceased for me to open, as God might help me, at her Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, to warn us; and as for my part I fear that a dismal Day is coming (of which I have often hinted to some of you) when perhaps (as one some years ago hath writen) such that <hi>Now walk the Streets in State shall run the Streets in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:207117:24"/> distraction</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="bottom">See <hi>Reeve</hi>'s, a Book called a Cry to <hi>Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh,</hi> or Gods Voice to <hi>London.</hi>
                  </note> The Crown I fear is near falling <hi>from our Heads, and we may say, wo to us, we have sinned,</hi> Lam. 5. 16. We may ere long, cry, <hi>Ichibod, the glory is departed,</hi> or where is the Glory? 1 Sam. 4. 21. We have many sad signs upon us as <hi>Jerusalem</hi> had, tho perhaps many see them not, nor will believe what I speak of, I wish it be not the removing the Gospel—is it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayled on us and on our Children? no, no, the Seven Churches in <hi>Asia</hi> lost it, their Candlesticks are long ago removed, <hi>France</hi> and the <hi>Palatinate</hi> once had it, but have now near lost it, O what a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful condition are the Witnesses of Christ or Saints of God in there, and look to it O <hi>England,</hi> is not thy Day near? <hi>are the witnesses yet slain? if not, what is Approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi> how have our Prophets been mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken? they have found no Vision, Lam. 2. 9. Or as the Spirit saith, <hi>they have seen vain and foolish things, they have not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered thine iniquities, but have seen for thee false burdens,</hi> ver. 14. Who is able to tell us, <hi>When will be the end of the Wonders</hi> what a <hi>Confederation</hi> is there at this time amongst the <hi>Popish Princes,</hi> how low is
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:207117:25"/> the <hi>Protestant Interest</hi> a broad? and how weak and divided at home? that Year, that some have oft Talk'd of, as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of our joys, may prove the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of our greater sorrows Sirs I am no Prophet, nor Son of a Prophet, but, <hi>Shall a Trumpet be blown in the City, and the People be not afraid? Amos 3. 6. The Lion hath roared, who will not fear? the Lord hath spoken? who can but Prophesy,</hi> ver. 8. The Symtoms and Signs we have upon us, are as when a Lion roareth when near his Prey, God seems to be angry, and will rise up and terribly, Shake both Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, if it prove <hi>Babylons</hi> ruin (for there it may Issue) yet, <hi>Who shall live when God doth this? Satan</hi> is come down in a great rage because his time is short, Let me here add some of those things which I fear are sad Presages of Approaching Miseries and cause of Weeping for our selves and for our Children.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What a Time of Spiritual Plenty have we had! how has <hi>England,</hi> espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>London</hi> been exalted to Heaven in respect of means, but hath this plenty been prized, and this great means Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved? have we served the Lord with joy of Heart, in the abundance of all things. Alas no! most of <hi>Professors</hi> have ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:207117:25"/> served themselves in a pursuit of the World and their own Worldly Interest. It seems as if there has been <hi>a price put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of fools that have had no heart to it,</hi> Prov. 17. 16. Therefore God may cause us <hi>to serve our Enemies with Hunger, and Nakedness, and in the want of all things,</hi> I fear a Famine is a coming, a Famine, but not of Bread. <hi>Behold the Days come, saith the Lord, that I will send a Famine in the Land, not a Famine of Bread, nor of Thirst of Water, but of Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Word of the Lord,</hi> Amos 8. 11. The Removal of the Gospel is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Judgment; the greatest Sign of God's anger was <hi>when the Glory went from the Cherubins,</hi> Ezek. 9. 2. The Gospel is the greatest Mercy a People can injoy, therefore the Taking it away must be the worst of Punishments: When that goes, God goes, Christ goes, and then <hi>Popery,</hi> the Devil, and all Evil comes, <hi>Wo to them when I depart.</hi> How little is it prized? Sound Doctrine is cast un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Contempt, and many are most plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with airy Speculations, and uncouth Notions. People rather hear to feed their Ears and Curiosities, than for Edification and Profit to their Souls; the Heavenly Manna is esteemed but
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:207117:26"/> light Bread; few will hear but at times, when they have nothing else to do, and when they hear the Word they will not do it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What sad Divisions, Strife and Contentions are amongst us, and what Contempt is cast upon the Authority of true Churches; nay, and what tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Churches to pieces, under the pretence of Zeal for God, when Pride, Ignorance and Self-Conceitedness is the cause of all. <hi>When the Sheep fight and quarrel one with another, the Shepherd fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telleth a Storm is near:</hi> Was there ever a more dismal Presage on this account upon a People than is amongst us? Yea, and it appears to be universal, <hi>i. e.</hi> amongst, People of all Perswasions. How do some Professors expose others and load them with Reproaches and Infamy. <hi>Report say they, and we will Report;</hi> 'tis the Voice of their Practices, if not of their Tongues.</p>
               <p n="3">3. How many faithful Ministers are taken away, (when a King calls home his Ambassadours, tis a sign he intends War): and how are they that are left behind slighted! what Arrows are let
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:207117:26"/> fly daily against them and what little care taken of them, or of some who some times were greatly esteemed! Some are look'd upon as Enemies for telling them the Truth, and how are some Truths and Ordinances decried for Errors, nay as bad as <hi>Popery</hi> that lie plain in Gods Word. Nay, and if you will vindicate; and practice them, look to't, you shall be under their new Persecution, your Consciences imposed on, or your Persons vilified, and this not in a Corner but Publickly. O Sirs, what can we look for!</p>
               <p n="4">4. How loose and carnal, earthly and worldly, the generality of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessers become? what difference do you see between Professors and the Prophane in many respects? Do but observe them in their Tradings, Converse, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versations, how like vain Wantons do the Daughters of <hi>Sion</hi> go. O the horrid Pride shewed in their Garbs and Dresses, and will not be reformed! where is that Holy, Heavenly and Humble walker with God. Do not many rest upon a meer profession, without the Life and Power of Religion? are there not now many foolish Virgins, nay are
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:207117:27"/> they not half of them such, who have Lamps and no Oil? what then? why look for the <hi>Midnight Cry,</hi> 'tis at the door.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Is not the horrid Prophaneness of these Times a Just ground to fear, that a Shower of Wrath and Divine Vengeance is a coming? was there worse Wickedness found in <hi>Sodom</hi> than is now in <hi>London,</hi> nay is not <hi>Sodomy</hi> and what not found in this City? Be asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, O ye Heavens! what is <hi>London</hi> a City of such Light, a place of Vision, become the Shame and Derision of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Have not our Fruits been Grapes of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and our Clusters of <hi>Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah,</hi> sure the Harvest is near Ripe for cutting down.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Is not <hi>Atheism, horried Errors,</hi> and Detestible Heresies (which never cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly so much abounded) a grand cause to fear a Dismal Hour is near? what old abominable Error and Heresie is not Broached among us Daily.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Is not the Contempt of all Revealed Religion and the treading Christ under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:207117:27"/> a sad symtom of Approaching Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Instead of being <hi>Christianized</hi> are we not in danger of being <hi>Paganized,</hi> while Natural Religion is cryed up as sufficient to save mens Souls; men will not believe things which their natural depraved Human Reason, cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend tho the Gospel is full of Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, yet some are so Bold to affirm there is nothing mysterious in it: But is it not a Mystery to believe Three to be One, and One to be Three; to believe the Father not older then the Son, and the Son to be equal with the Father; to believe in one nature there are three Persons, and in one Person two Natures; to believe the <hi>Ancient of Days</hi> to become a <hi>Babe of a Day old,</hi> to believe a <hi>Virgin</hi> to have been a <hi>Mother,</hi> and her Son to be her Creator, to believe a man is freely forgiven and Pardoned; and yet all his Debts were fully paid; to believe we are Just and without Sin, and yet Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and that we are Justified and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous by another Righteousness. I say some, these are your Fancies and Idle Dreams; why so? because they by their Human Reason can't comprehend them. And thus to these Gentiles, the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Gospel is accounted <hi>foolishness</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>